Okay I think we still have a few people
logging in, but I think we're gonna go ahead
and get started. Just a little um a few notes for tonight, we are working with tech support
because we should have a discussion uh panel
that will allow you to post questions during
our panel, um and also we have time for questions
at the end before we do go into 101 chats.
So um we do have somebody from our team who's
on with tech support so hopefully we'll get that
panel going soon. Once we do get that going just so
you know any question that you post in the panel
um everyone will be able to see that that
will be public so just be aware of that
as well, and then I'm also going to go ahead
and try and share my screen. I'm at work so
I have two monitors so just give me
one second to play around with that.
Okay can everyone see that okay? For my
panelists can you give me a thumbs up if
you can see that, perfect, and at least for
my panelists are you able to hear me okay?
Yes. Very good so we're gonna go ahead and get
started I'll start by um introducing myself
my name is Jen Heinold I'm one of the assistant
directors with Career and Professional Development,
one of my roles is to serve as liaison to the
College of Science which is um kind of how this
event got started today and I will let um my other
panelists introduce themselves uh Dr. Emori if you
want to go ahead? Hi my name is Meg Emori and I
am the, one of the instructors in Principles of
Biology. I also teach the Careers in Biological
Sciences course if you're interested in that.
Hi all my name is Annie Laib-Jenkins
and I work as the assistant director
of Health Professions Advising within
Career and Professional Development.
Awesome, so I am getting a note here from tech
support if you all would give me one second um
eh we're gonna pause for just about 30
seconds they should be able to refresh
our feed, and then we should be able to see
our discussion panel. While they're doing that
um basically what what we're gonna do tonight
is uh we are going to um really just talk about
ways to get involved, ways to be make yourself
competitive for what it is that you want to do.
We know a lot of students just don't quite know
how to get started, what should they be doing
um to be competitive. So that's what we're going
to talk you through tonight. We're going to give
you some timelines as well on essentially um you
know if you are applying for grad school, if you
are applying for health professions, we're going
to go through some general timelines, but we're
also going to talk about gap years and things like
that. And it does sound like everyone will need to
refresh for us to get our panel up so we can take
your questions so let's go ahead and take a minute
if everyone will go ahead and refresh um their
browsers. If you get kicked out just log back on
and then we'll go ahead and get started with our
content. So we'll see everybody back here in just a
minute.
And it looks like I'm still going and
we are recording, it looks like I got
everybody back and most importantly it
looks like we have our discussion panel.
So very good um and then if my other
panelists can help me moderate that
as I get going that would be great. I am
going to go ahead and re-share my screen.
Okay very good, so the reason um one of the
reasons we want to go ahead and go through
this is essentially if if students don't do
anything during their time at Virginia Tech,
and unfortunately I've certainly had some of those
appointments where students aren't very involved,
what happens is essentially the resume can look
something like this if you just have your degree
this is all that's going to be on your resume. And
we've definitely had students who for whatever
reason maybe they just didn't know what to do, um
maybe because they didn't know what they want to
do, they didn't know what to get involved in, and so
they kind of get that you know paralysis of oh I'm
just not going to do anything. So even if you're
not sure the most important thing we hope you get
out of today is even if you're not sure what you want
to do, if you have a general idea, if you have no
idea, um just start getting involved in something.
um Because it's going to not only help you
explore but at least it's going to be something to
get you going, to get you building your network, and
to get something going on your resume. One place
you might want to start is discover this website
experience.vt.edu I haven't had a ton of time to
play around with it. I'm actually doing a webinar
about it uh this Friday um so I wish it was last
Friday because I would have known a little bit
more. But I played around with it a little bit
and I do feel like they have some tools that can
be really helpful for students. um The my map to
kind of help you maybe plan things out, um Clifton
Strengths if you haven't done your strengths is
a great self-assessment tool to just learn more
about yourself and your strengths, um and that can
be really helpful for students. The reflections
piece I I really think is helpful because
sometimes what happens too is students do do a lot
of really good things, but they may be like wait
and it's junior year and they're updating their
resume for the first time since freshman year, and
they've done all this stuff but they really don't
remember much about it, and so now it becomes hard
to really update that. So I would say maybe once
you know at the end of each semester, and even at
the end of summer, take some time to update your
resume and really almost make a master resume out
of it. um Write some reflections about what you did
if you had a really good team working experience
right about that as it happens um because
as you get closer when you're doing interviews
and stuff like that whether it's for an internship
for a graduate program you know for an actual job
after graduation those are the types of questions
you're going to get in that situation, and those
are things that you're going to write about in
your personal statement and your cover letter. So
take two or three times a year and not only update
your resume, but do that reflections piece as
well. So again if you're not sure what to do just
getting started I think experience.vt.edu
can be a great place for you to start.
Jen just to pop in for a moment it looks
as though at least one of our students is
having a challenge seeing your powerpoint, um
I know I can see it okay but I just wanted to
let you know that that's happening in the
discussion right now. Okay, is anyone else having
any issue go ahead and post that into
the discussion if anyone else
is having a problem seeing it.
I will be sending out resources tomorrow to
everybody that was registered for the event
tonight. So I can send a copy of the slides as well
um I'm getting feedback from our tech support it
sounds like you should be able to see so you can
always try refreshing um like you did before and
see if that helps, but thank you for letting us
know. So what are some other ways to get experience?
And this is by no means an exhaust- exhaustive
list but let's go ahead and go through this a
little bit so job shadowing can be a great way to
um explore you know especially if you are trying
to determine a certain path to go down talking to
actual professionals is one of the best things you
can do. Sometimes I think it's even more
helpful than classes um to actually talk about
what do you do, what are your challenges, what do
you love most about your job, what advice would
you give a student who's wanting to do this. um So
talking to professionals whether it's you know an
actual job shadow, or just an informational
interview can be so so helpful and Annie
will talk a little bit later, but especially for
those that are interested in Health Professions
those clinical shadowing hours are going to
be expected of you. um So just be aware of
that. Volunteering, obviously I think can be a
great way to get involved and gain so many of
those personal skills that we know employers and
graduate programs are looking for, that teamwork,
that leadership, those communication skills. um So
sometimes I feel like students kind of downplay
volunteering and I think it's a wonderful way to
explore and gain a lot of those skills as well.
Internships are pretty obvious um and yes they're
definitely a good resume builder I see a lot of
internships from my juniors, right between junior
and senior year. That's probably where we see them
the most. um We certainly do have some sophomores
that are able to get internships, and occasionally
we do get freshmen. But I will say I've had a lot
of appointments recently by freshmen who feel like
they're, it seems like they're expected to have, or
they think they're expected to have an internship
and I can tell you an employer down the road is
not going to expect you to have an internship
after freshman year. If you can get one, that's
outstanding, but if you think about what an
internship is, it's really designed to be a very
structured program where you are doing actual
work for that employer and in return that employer
is giving you an experience to help educate you on
the field and you know build your resume and make
you you know more prepared to enter that field.
So because of that you do have to have a certain
background for most internships, um and most
freshmen just aren't going to have the coursework
or the experience to be ready for some of those
experiences. Again there can be exceptions to that
so I would never tell a freshman not to apply
but I also think it's important to be open-minded
especially in our current job situation.
The economy is rebounding but it's going
to take several years to really recover
from all that is probably for us to right to
really recover from everything that has happened
over the last year not just the economy. So be
open to all of these other opportunities as well.
And that takes me to general employment. I cannot
tell you how many times we have students that
downplay their work experience. I just worked
at the dining hall, I was only a lifeguard over
the summer, our office can help you think about and
speak about and highlight all the wonderful skills
that you learned in that experience. So don't
ever downplay employment. College is expensive,
um a lot of times students need to work to either
help pay their bills, or for their spending money,
or whatever the case may be. um I met with a
student earlier today they had to finance 75%
of her education. She had to work a lot,
and so we talked about that on her resume
and all the different skills that she gained
from that experience. So don't downplay
employment. Field study, we see this there are
some majors on campus that have a field study
component that's built in as part of the degree
requirement. It usually takes place takes place in
the senior year. So if you're thinking about
a major that has a field study component, or
you're in a major that has a field study
component I would say just be aware of that um
and think about what you want that experience
to be, so that by the time you get there again
you're competitive you know for that experience
because usually you do have to apply for that.
Service learning is another wonderful opportunity,
now obviously we haven't done as much of this in
the last year as we have previously. Virginia
Tech is really big on service learning
um this is a little challenging right now because
it's hard for students to physically go into a lot
of spaces as we know, um but hopefully as we look
forward to the next couple years we can get back
to some of these activities. And kind of tied
to that there's another experience that's not
on this list that probably should be and that's
study abroad. um There are some really cool short
term service learning study abroad trips that
can be a wonderful experience. um Right now they
are approving study abroad on a case-by-case
basis. But we do have about 50 Virginia Tech
students that are studying abroad this semester.
So that is starting to open up a little bit and
again that can be another wonderful experience.
um So if it's something you're thinking about
there are those short-term programs if you can't
do a whole summer or semester, or obviously we
have those experiences as well. So make sure you
get in touch with the global education office
if you have any thoughts of study abroad
because the earlier you can plan the better.
And then obviously student organizations I I know
this also looks different, um but one thing I love
about student organizations is um if you can get
started early freshman or sophomore year then a
lot of times by junior senior year you can get
into those leadership positions, which often look
so good on resumes. I also think this is a great
way to find balance so I encourage students to
maybe get involved in one or two organizations
that are going to be related to your career goals, to
your major so those resume builders, but find one
or two that are just fun. I know you're not having
as much fun as honestly you probably should, I
think having fun is important part of college. I
actually really do and I know that doesn't look
the same as it has in the past, um but you know
joining one or two organizations to just meet your
people to to just you know do something that you
enjoy that stress relief is so important as well
and then you balance that out with the other ones.
And again if you're not sure where to start
join one, right join one or two keep it small. um
That's totally fine don't jump in and join ten
all of a sudden because time management's gonna
be really important as well um you can always add
on more but if you're not sure just join one or
just you know you know look on Gobbler Connect and
contact somebody. Be like hey can I just come to a
meeting and see what it's about? I know those are
going to be virtual um but you know that's a great
way to build your resume too. And then the last
thing I have on the list is research. If you're
thinking about um you know certainly this can be
helpful for health professions, but definitely any
stem-based graduate program um I think research
is is a key component to have on your resume. um
Also if you're interested in actually going into
research of any kind we obviously have a lot of
science students who are thinking about that as
a possible option, it can be so important. So I'm
going to go ahead and turn it over to Dr. Emori and
she's going to talk about that a little bit more.
All right so if you're interested in getting
involved on- in research on campus by far the best
resource for you is the Office of Undergraduate
Research. So there's a website um they will have
resources to help you get into research,
they highlight research opportunities,
if you're printing a poster and you're a student
doing research they can help with that, they can
even help you with some travel funding. What I
particularly want to highlight about this resource
is the student ambassadors. So these
are students who have successfully
tried to get into research, gotten into
research, they are doing research, um and
they're volunteering their time to help you
with this process as well so you don't have to
sort of reinvent the wheel in terms of what am
I supposed to do. Go ahead and turn the slide.
All right so I'm going to break down
how to get into research in four steps.
So the first step is that you need to be a
competitive applicant, so unfortunately we don't
have as many faculty as we do students on campus,
and so ultimately there isn't research positions
available for every single student. So doing things
like keeping up your GPA is really useful but
also thinking about getting into classes that will
help pave the way to the research you want to do.
So if you're interested in an immunology lab it
might make sense to take immunology. All right
next up- next click. All right so now (that) you're a
competitive applicant how do you find faculty to
do research? So to do this I like to go on to the
departmental websites. You can either look at the
faculty tab or the research tab, every department's
a little different but what you're looking for
is a listing of faculty members. Usually
it has a little picture of their face,
a link to their own lab website, and a little
blurb about what they do. So this is by far
the fastest and efficien- most efficient way
to sort of see who's doing what around campus.
And please don't limit yourself to your own
department, there are computer scientists doing
research in physics, biologists doing research in
chemistry, and so by no means do you need to keep
yourself just to your own department. Again.
All right so now you have to reach out to
these faculty members. So in your email always
include your name, how far you are along, why you're
interested in their lab, think about how much time
do you have to offer, do you want to start this
semester, do you want to start next semester, do
you have two hours, do you have five hours a week?
This will help them sort of gauge how you can fit
into their lab, and again talk about any previous
lab experience you've had. If you've had immunology,
if you're applying to immunology lab the things
that you have been doing to get ready for this
opportunity now most of us faculty members are
a little bit swamped with email um so once you
send out an email it's okay to wait a week or two
if you haven't heard from us please email again
um that's respectful thing you're not bothering
us if after two emails you haven't heard then
it's probably a bad semester things are just a
little crazy um and reach out again maybe next
semester if you really want to be in that lab
the last thing i will say on this is be mindful
that we as faculty even though we're all working
from home mostly now we still talk to each other
um and so try not to email every single professor
in an entire department at once because that makes
us feel like you just want a live body and that
makes us much less interested in you as a student
right whereas if you email two or three at a time
then we think oh you really are interested in
what research we are doing so i would say two
to three at a time and then just keep moving down
that list depending on again we're in covid not
all labs are working at full steam yet so there
you go and last one last thing i want to say is
you can do research as a study abroad opportunity
so there are research opportunities across the us
great for summer research when i was an undergrad
i did research in germany so you can even do your
study abroad as a research experience and that's
a wonderful opportunity too all right back to you
very much for covering that so i also want to
just talk about our office a little bit and all
the ways that we can help you so even from the
very beginning if you're just i don't know what
i want to do i'm not sure major wise career-wise
any of that we have lots of resources to help you
in addition to our staff we have self-assessments
um we can help walk you through um you know
walk you through okay that every major
and career it's not always linear
um and so we can kind of talk through that process
oftentimes i think thinking about career first
and then backtracking to majors actually makes
more sense because the majority of careers you
can do with a variety of majors occasionally there
is a linear path certain things like to sit for a
cpa you do have to have certain accounting classes
which means at some point you're probably going to
complete an accounting program right that does
exist for sure but the vast majority of careers
you can do with any major so we can kind of help
you navigate that because it can be overwhelming
um we're happy to talk to you again about certain
qualifications and things like that that might
make sense or make you more competitive for
certain careers or certain uh graduate programs
as well as annie will talk about we're here
for all everything health professions so it
doesn't matter what health professions
you're thinking about or interested in
the sooner you connect with the house health
professions team here at uh career impression
development the better because it is they are all
unique in their own way um in terms of process um
and they can definitely help you navigate that and
and be as competitive as an applicant as possible
we do a lot of resume and cover letter reviews
and right now we are doing a ton of resume reviews
um so you know i've been talking about resumes a
lot and you know getting experience so you have
something to talk about but a lot of students
don't even know really how to format a resume
there's some bad templates out there i'm going to
be honest with you um so definitely take advantage
of our office we can help you with that a lot of
students don't realize in terms of employment a
lot of employers use tracking systems so it's
not even a person that's looking at your resume
and there are certain things you're going to need
to do to make sure you can make it through those
systems so we're more than happy to help you with
your resume and your cover letter we also a lot of
students don't even know where to start in terms
of searching okay i think i want an internship in
in area x but i don't know where to start let us
help you walk through that process because there's
a lot of job search engines and a lot of resources
out there that can be valuable and helpful but you
can end up spending four hours one day just going
down the rabbit hole and have nothing to show for
it so you know we're here to help you go through
that process as well i'm going to talk a little
bit about graduate school tonight and planning
for that and that's another area where we can help
and then let's say you get to a point where you
actually get an interview we can do a practice
interviews with you we have a lot of students that
will do practice interviews with us and that can
be so so helpful especially on how to navigate
that behavioral interview and how to best talk
about your experiences and then finally if you're
in a situation where you actually have an offer
first of all yay that's amazing um we can talk to
you about negotiations are you able to negotiate
that offer what are you able to negotiate if
you're fortunate enough to have more than one
offer what should you be considering to make that
decision so this is just an example of all the
ways our office is here to help this is a picture
of our main website so if you click on that career
resources and advising for students it's going to
take you to a list that's basically going to go
through a lot of the things i talked about and
resources associated with those to schedule an
appointment with our office you're going to want
to go to our website and actually go to handshake
handshake is a wonderful platform so you're
going to want to set up an account it's free
you should do that so you can schedule with
us you can obviously find events like the one
that you're doing tonight along with a lot of
other info sessions we have a lot of employers
that are posting information sessions right now um
health professions does a ton of events and even
jobs whether it's a local you know part-time
campus part-time job internship opportunity
full-time jobs those all get posted on handshake
as well so definitely spend some time with that
and then you know when i talk about networking
again if you go to our website you can also go
to hokey mentorship connect that is our alumni
mentoring platform so when i talk about reaching
out to alumni reaching out to people that are in
these various fields that you're interested in
um definitely take advantage of hokie mentorship
connect we have over a thousand alumni on there
that want to help students they were students
they know what this process is like they know
how overwhelming it can be so certainly you
know make sure you check that out as well
and now we're going to kind of switch gears a
little bit and we are going to start talking about
grad school so grad school can be a wonderful
experience all of us on the panel have been
through grad school um what grad school is not is
it's probably not a good place to find yourself
it's a very expensive and trying time to do that
or at least it can be so when you're thinking
about grad school i think it's important to first
of all have at least some direction i don't think
you have to have like that that first career and
i do say first because you're probably gonna have
many careers um i don't think you need to have
like it pinpointed exactly but i do think it's
helpful to have a general direction before you
commit to a graduate program i definitely think
um that's certainly helpful um you're
not going to be taking gen eds you're
not going to be taking electives and if you
are they're going to be tied to your program
so put some thought into that i know sometimes
we have students that are like well maybe the
job market's down and i'll go to grad school i
know dr emery did that but she went to harvard
and had funding so that's a little bit of a
different situation um especially if you've taken
on a lot if you already have a lot of loans after
undergrad i know i had loans after undergrad um
you just want to really put a lot of thought
into it before you take on more debt especially
heading into a graduate program i get very mama
bear about that but it can be very expensive
the next thing you want to look at is are you
competitive for admission so once you kind of
have that general direction of what you want to
do you're going to start looking at programs when
you're looking at programs you really want to do
as much research on those websites to find out
what do i need to be competitive and then do some
some reflection and be honest with yourself am i
there and if not what do i need to do to get there
and again that's where you know everyone here
you know is happy to help you with that um but
definitely you know want to look into that as well
next thing i talked about you know financing
um can you afford it finance it or get funding
so um as i mentioned i'm going
to be sending out resources
um to everyone that registered tonight one of
those resources is going to be handout on funding
it is especially it is geared especially more
towards uh stem fields because we do know right
now there tends to be more funding available
for stem fields but it's going to go through
the different opportunities for funding kind of
based on um based on lots of different things so
there's going to be a lot of links on there for
you um but as i mentioned i think it's important
to think about that especially before you take on
additional debt and there's lots of ways you can
get funding as well so you will be getting that
later um it's hard to go in a lot of the specifics
in the time we have tonight but i just wanted you
to know that that's going to be coming for you
so the next thing is can you handle the workload
um graduate school i think most people would tell
you for the most part every program is a little
bit different and there's so many different
programs out there right now but it's typically
more challenging and there's going to be more
expected of you than undergrad that's going to
be especially true for health professions zany's
going to address but especially for those that
are leading towards you know a master's degree
or a phd in a stem field i feel like that um
you know can be it's going to be challenging
uh before i start working at virginia tech i
worked at the university of illinois for about
11 years and i was in general studies for five
years of that as an academic advisor so i had a
lot worked with a lot of students that came into
college thinking i'm going to go to med school
and they'd start taking some of those classes and
i had a lot of appointments where students would
say well if i just get through this then i'm gonna
go to med school and i try to do it in a funny way
but i had to have some real conversations along
the lines of here's the thing med school makes
undergrad look like preschool so if you're not
getting through this you're not gonna get through
med school right and i don't say that to be mean
but you know that was the mentality and so just
be aware there's gonna be a lot expected of you
um but again it's it's a wonderful opportunity
i you will learn more than you ever will
but if you need a break we're going to talk
about a gap year so that's something else
to keep in mind too if you're like i want
to do it but i really need a break that's an
option as well so we'll talk about that too
and then lastly when you start doing all this
research and you have kind of that direction
right so you want to kind of have that that
career direction to go into start looking
at what those jobs look what is the job market
like and will going to grad school actually make
you more marketable for a lot of professions
um the answer is going to be yes but not always
depending on what you want to do you might be
more competitive or better off just going into
the workforce and getting actual experience before
um as you know as opposed to going to grad school
and the other thing when you think of all this and
especially think of the financing the money too
even if you are funded which is awesome um you're
not really making money most funding is enough to
cover your living expenses while you're there
but it's not the same as bringing home like an
actual salary during that time so if it is like
a health professions or phd program that that's
going to go on for several years you definitely
want to just factor that in as well so again i'll
be giving you that other resource but i feel like
these are the main considerations to think about
if you're deciding whether or not to do grad
school or at least do grad school right away
so this is a very general timeline i don't want
you to think you're stuck on this but this is
just to give you an idea for a student who would
be starting a stem-based program um immediately
after uh graduating um you know their undergrad
here at tech so freshman year typically and and
again i'll send out copies of the slides so
you have them so if you can't see this 100
clearly um if you make your screen full screen
if you haven't done that yet it might help but
you want to establish a good gpa but i'm going to
talk about how it's okay if you had a rough year
um really start exploring get any experience you
can we talked about just join that one club just
start doing something is better than nothing and
then you may to stay on track it may be easier
if you start taking prereqs your freshman year
obviously if you're still exploring sometimes you
may be doing a little bit of ketchup on those
and that's okay so the other thing i'll say
about gpa is we do know a lot of freshmen um don't
always have the best freshman year college is hard
it's an adjustment and especially in this virtual
world it's an adjustment um i personally know
people that have law degrees and phds that were on
probation after their freshman year of college so
you're using resources and you have a plan on how
to recover but again i personally have worked with
people who have gone on to really great graduate
programs after not having a great freshman year
but they were able to come back and their programs
were able to see that upward trend so just be
aware of that sophomore year obviously you want
to try and either bring up or maintain a gpa
if you can start getting involved in research
that's great if not definitely need to do it by
junior year um volunteering and then probably
you know definitely getting started on prereqs
junior year pretty much working on the gpa getting
involved in research volunteering or getting
involved you know in other ways um and then
you need to start researching your programs for
sure at this point if you haven't already um and
then we get to summer before senior year now in
a pre-covered world you would have to be studying
for and taking a gre or some type of entrance exam
i don't know what's going to happen with these
moving forward i know a lot of programs have
waived these for this year because of covid and
not being able to have access across the board
0:30:10.160,1193:02:47.295
you can recover you just want to make sure that
you're working hard with your academic advisor
um you know for these exams but some of them are
going to require them again some of them might not
i don't know what's going to happen so this is
where doing that program research is so important
on because they you may have programs that
require it you may have some other optional
and you may have some where they don't and then
typically again if you're going to go right
after senior year fall senior year getting
all your stuff together um if you have to
retake your exam start working on your personal
statement is so important that reflection piece
so you have stuff to talk about and then with
recommendation letters please don't i know dr
emory don't spring those on them the last minute
um give them time give them a copy of your resume
but throughout these other years be building
those relationships that's the important thing um
you know just because you got an a in somebody's
class doesn't mean they know you well enough to
write a really strong personal letter so i know
virtual office hours are not as fun and easy as
um you know in person office hours but make sure
that you are still building those relationships
so you have people that can write you really
strong letters and then finally you would finalize
everything typically december again can vary by
program um april 15th is your decision deadline
and then most programs start july or august
um but what you don't see in here and i know
annie's gonna agree with me on this is i don't
see a lot of sleep and i don't see a lot of fun
um so guess what you can do a gap year um they're
more and more common they're more and more popular
it gives you an extra year to do all the things i
just talked about in three years it gives you four
years to do that there are some wonderful like
opportunities during one or more gap years there
are some post baccalaureate opportunities that
are pretty research oriented but they're that's
a wonderful opportunity they are competitive
but that's a great thing to do in a gap year
there are just other cool programs that are you
know a couple years things like americorps things
like the peace corps but you can also just get
a job a lot of students don't realize that they
think that first job is is this major commitment
right now pre-covered on average time students
were spending in their first job after graduation
is about 14 months so it is not uncommon to only
stay in that first position for a year or two so
that is another opportunity for you as well and
i feel like a lot of students don't necessarily
realize that um so all of us on the panel we're
big fans of gap years um and we are happy to kind
of talk you through what should i do what can i do
but if you need more time to be sure to be
ready and be competitive this is you know
one or more gap years is a wonderful opportunity
and we really encourage that and with that i'm
going to pass it along to annie who's going to
specifically talk about um the preparation for
health professions programs excellent thank you
so much jen so yes everything that jen said about
gap years i will reiterate tenfold so i'm going to
talk a little bit about the timeline into health
professions for those of you that are interested
in med school dental school vet school ptot or
anything in between that's pre-health that's
what we're here for so the first thing if you
take nothing else away from this conversation
is that i want you to remember that if you are
pre-health it is a marathon not a sprint so
what i mean by that is that the application
cycle from the time you apply to the time that
you would start a health professional program
it's typically just about a year and many students
take many years leading up to that application
to build the experience and the competencies that
they need to develop to be a competitive applicant
so i want you to keep in mind it's a marathon
not a sprint so let's talk about what you can
do to get started so i think it probably goes
without saying that academics are important if
you're interested in a health profession they're
necessary they're not sufficient but it is a
necessary thing that we need to consider to have
a strong academic record professional schools
are going to be asking hey if we admit this
student do we have faith that that student can
be successful when they get into the program and
your undergraduate record is your best proxy to
convince them that yes they should have faith in
your ability to be successful and then we've got
two sub questions underneath that number one is
can you handle a science curriculum right so that
means being successful in your course work namely
your science coursework in particular but really
overall and then question number two is okay but
can you handle the academic rigor so jen mentioned
this earlier but professional school doesn't
look like undergrad undergrad i lovingly call
the swiss cheese schedule you all have a class
and then nap time and then a class and then you
get to go get a snack and then a class and then
maybe you study a little bit and rinse and repeat
that monday through friday professional school
isn't really like that they put you in class from
the morning until the evening monday through
friday and then they send you home to study
so they want to make sure that students can handle
academic intensity so as we think about this the
first thing that you want to be doing is starting
as strong as you possibly can like jen said
academic recovery is possible but it's a whole lot
easier to start strong than have to dig yourself
out of a hole later so we can discuss that but you
want to make sure that you get your footing and
that you feel really good academically first once
you feel like you've got your feet underneath you
if you can handle taking 15 plus credits per
term and you're a pre-health student that's a
general recommendation of the pre-health office
just so that you can demonstrate your ability to
handle academic rigor so on top of that as you get
started please seek out advising every one of you
has an academic advisor and if you're a pre-health
student you've got three full-time staff members
that specifically work with pre-health students to
help them on their journey to a health profession
so please utilize us our office is called health
professions advising we're nested within career
and professional development we encourage the
students meet with us at least once a year but
if you're on a truncated timeline like let's say
you're a transfer student or you're graduating
early even more often than that would be ideal
the next thing is join the hpa hub on canvas
so what this is it's a canvas page where we can
send announcements opportunities and events to you
as pre-health students and it's also a repository
of resources that may be useful to you you can
join it from our website so the career services
website is career.vt.edu and then add a forward
slash hpa and you'll get to the webpage of career
professional development that's specifically
for health professions advising and at the top
right of that you can click join the hpa hub
on canvas and we will get you added so i would
strongly encourage you to do that okay so now
we want to talk about engagement you've got your
feet underneath you academically you're on the
hub you know where your advisor is we want to talk
about what you need to do to become competitive so
the first thing that i want to say here is that it
sounds a little bit like a checklist but you can't
treat it like a checklist okay as i start talking
about experiences what i want you to think about
is that professional schools are looking for
interesting people so if you're following your
intrinsic motivations as you gain some of these
foundational experiences you're doing it the right
way if you're treating it like a checklist that
you have to check the boxes on you're doing it
the wrong way so we want to think about that but
it's really important to get clinical experiences
so professional programs first they're gonna
wonder does this student actually know what
they're getting into right if you tell me you're a
pre-med student and you're applying to med school
but you've never ever interacted with a doctor or
gone to a hospital to shadow doctors how should
i believe you right so you want to make sure that
you're having observational experiences that will
be able to answer that question then our other
question that professional schools are going
to want to know is is this person going to be
good at working with patients do they want to
work with sick people are they excited about
that right so to answer that question you want
to be gaining direct patient care experience so
emt experience certified nursing aid experience
a hospice volunteer medical assistant those sorts
of roles that can put you in contact with patients
and teach you do you really want to work
with patients and then provide evidence to
an admissions committee of the same next we want
to talk about leadership so what i would say here
is that leadership is not limited to being the
president of a club or an organization certainly
that's one way to demonstrate leadership but we
want to be thinking beyond that right professional
schools are looking for people that can take
initiative that have go-getter attitudes that can
work with other people even through challenging
situations that have grit that have resilience
leadership roles and leadership experiences can
help you to gain those things so leadership could
mean training other people it could mean
tutoring it could mean being a ta it could
mean being a mentor or a role model to others it
could mean taking initiative towards a cause that
you care about all perfectly valid ways to gain
leadership but we want to be thinking about that
you want to be thinking about service if you're
going into a health profession you're going into a
service oriented profession so you need to have a
heart for serving others around you and admissions
committees expect to see that so we're looking
for service that is both regular and sustained
regular meaning you do it every week or every
other week or once a month you don't do it once a
year and call it done sustained meaning you don't
do it for two months and stop right you continue
doing this because you're passionate about it and
you care about it and recognize that some programs
specifically define community service is working
with the disadvantaged population of people so you
want to be mindful of that and then there's the
other stuff right research if you're excited about
it the hobbies the extracurriculars so once you
get engaged you want to maintain your involvement
this is so that you can be building
competencies through doing these experiences
and i would strongly encourage you to
journal about these experiences so that
you can remember these stories so when it comes
time to interview or write a personal statement
you'll be ready to go it's really important to
make meaning out of the things that you've done
so as you get a little bit closer to applying
you want to start making a list of schools and
visiting schools that you might be interested
in how long that list is going to be varies
from profession to profession but for those of you
for example that are pre-med we usually recommend
that students apply to 15 to 20 schools so it's
a pretty hefty list when all is said and done
next you want to be prepping for your admissions
exams the gre for example looks very different
than the mcat so you need to know what admissions
exam you're expected to take for your health
profession of interest and then you need to do
some research on how long you should expect to
study for that exam and how you should expect
to study for that exam because like i said the
gre and mcat very different tests very different
timelines for studying and a very different study
process for those exams so come talk to hpa
if you have questions we can help you on that
okay so after that recognize that many
programs strongly encourage what we
call a committee letter of evaluation so health
professions advising offers something called the
health professions evaluation committee or hpec
for sure for short which provides you with this
committee letter of evaluation think about this
as kind of like a rec letter but in a rec letter
the person that's writing it typically knows
you really well but in a limited scope right
it might be a faculty member that you took a class
with so they know your performance in that class
and that you came to office hours every
week and you were a highly engaged student
in contrast the person that writes this committee
letter doesn't necessarily know you well
but they know the pool of applicants
that tend to apply to health professions
and so through you putting together a packet of
information and interviewing with that individual
they can have a really good idea of how your
strengths line up with that pool of applicants and
they can write this macro scale perspective letter
for you as an applicant and then of course apply
remembering that this is a year-long process
typically so for a student that is not wanting to
take a gap year that means applying in the summer
after their junior year for most programs but
like jen said taking a gap year is really common
and in health professions we are seeing like for
medical school for example the vast majority of
the applicants in the 2019 to 2020 cycle which is
the last cycle i have data on the vast majority of
them we're taking at least one if not multiple gap
years so do keep that in mind there's no right
time to apply you need to be competitive first
but that's all i've got for you i'm
going to turn it back over to jen
so let's go ahead and do this in the interest
of time um i will stay on um the lobby area
here and answer general questions if you have a
general question that you want to put in the chat
otherwise meg i'll have you go ahead and go to the
um the general booth and annie go ahead and go to
the hpa booth so we have two booths where you can
get in line and do individual one-on-one chat um
either with somebody from our health professions
team or we have meg my supervisor liam lee's from
career professional development is going to be
in the general booth as well so you're welcome
to go ahead and leave the lobby and go ahead and
enter one of those booths if you have specific
questions if you want to have a little bit of
a conversation if you have general questions
and you want to post them in the discussion
i'm happy to answer those um here as well
but thank you everybody um for coming and
hopefully you got some good information and
again i will be sending follow-up resources
for everybody who's registered tonight
you